Hello my name is David Brown and this is a pronunciation class. Hi David. I'm
مرحباً، اسمي ديفيد براون وهذا درس في النطق. مرحباً ديفيد. أنا
fine thank you. How are you? I'm doing great. Thank you. Thank you. Welcome. Thank
بخير شكراً لك. كيف حالك؟ أنا بخير جداً. شكراً لك. شكراً لك. أهلاً بك.
Thank you, David. Are you ready for your lesson today? Yes. All right. All right. Well we
شكراً لك يا ديفيد. هل أنت مستعد لدرس اليوم؟ نعم. حسناً. حسناً. إذاً يمكننا
can practice this lesson that I see that you selected. We have this short
أن نتدرب على هذا الدرس الذي أرى أنك اخترته. لدينا هذا الصوت القصير
i sound and then this long e sound the short i sound is like /ɪ/ and then the
لحرف i ثم هذا الصوت الطويل لحرف e. الصوت القصير لحرف i يشبه /ɪ/ ثم
long e sound is like /iː/, right? Okay. This is important for us to master because it
الصوت الطويل لحرف e يشبه /iː/، أليس كذلك؟ حسناً. من المهم لنا أن نتقن هذا لأنه
can cause confusion for native English speakers and it's a really
يمكن أن يسبب التباساً للمتحدثين الأصليين باللغة الإنجليزية وهو حقاً
commonly mispronounced pair. So we have some examples here. Some funny
زوج من الأصوات يُخطأ في نطقه بشكل شائع. لدينا بعض الأمثلة هنا. بعض الأمثلة
examples. We have fill and feel, sit and seat, chip and
المضحكة. لدينا fill و feel، و sit و seat، و chip و
cheap. This one is bit. This one is beat, beat, ship and this one is sheep. This
cheap. هذه bit. وهذه beat, beat, ship وهذه sheep. هذه
is lid and this one is lead. All right. So we need to know the difference
lid وهذه lead. حسناً. إذاً نحتاج إلى معرفة الفرق بين صوت
between the /ɪ/ sound and the /iː/ sound, the /ɪ/ sound and the /iː/ sound. Okay. The
/ɪ/ وصوت /iː/، صوت /ɪ/ وصوت /iː/. حسناً.
short /ɪ/ versus the /iː/ sounds. So this is what we'll practice in today's lesson. Two
صوت /ɪ/ القصير مقابل صوت /iː/ الطويل. هذا ما سنتدرب عليه في درس اليوم. صوتان
different sounds. For example, what is this? This is ship*, ship, very good. And this
مختلفان. على سبيل المثال، ما هذا؟ هذا ship*, ship، جيد جداً. وهذا،
one, these are, these are sheep. These are sheep, right? Regular plural noun. So we're
هذه sheep. هذه sheep، أليس كذلك؟ اسم جمع منتظم. إذاً نحن
looking at two English sounds that can be a little bit tricky but are very, very
ننظر إلى صوتين في اللغة الإنجليزية قد يكونان مربكين قليلاً ولكنهما مهمان جداً جداً
important for clear speaking. We want to understand and be understood and this can
للتحدث بوضوح. نريد أن نفهم وأن نُفهم وهذا يمكن أن
impact our comprehension. So it can change the meaning of words. We have this one
يؤثر على استيعابنا. لذا يمكن أن يغير معنى الكلمات. لدينا هذا
which is ship and this one which is cheap and that is just one example. So today we
وهو ship وهذا وهو cheap وهذا مجرد مثال واحد. إذاً اليوم لدينا
have two objectives here. I'd like for you to listen to these objectives. Today you
هدفان هنا. أود منكم الاستماع إلى هذه الأهداف. اليوم
will learn to hear the difference between /ɪ/ and /iː/ and say /ɪ/ and /iː/ more clearly. Let's
ستتعلمون سماع الفرق بين /ɪ/ و /iː/ وقول /ɪ/ و /iː/ بشكل أوضح. دعنا
try this. Can you repeat it for me? /ɪ/. Now, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/. Awesome. And so we have a little
نجرب هذا. هل يمكنك التكرار ورائي؟ /ɪ/. الآن، /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/. رائع. ولدينا نشاط صغير
activity here to practice. I said that you would need something like a stick and something
هنا للتدرب. قلت إنك ستحتاج إلى شيء مثل عصا وشيء
like a block. So I have a colored pencil and one of my daughter's blocks. Do you have
مثل مكعب. لذا لدي قلم رصاص ملون وأحد مكعبات ابنتي. هل لديك
something? Okay, yes, yes, I have something. Okay, okay, like this. Alright, so let's
شيء؟ حسناً، نعم، نعم، لدي شيء. حسناً، حسناً، كهذا. حسناً، إذاً دعنا
imagine that we have the /ɪ/ sound and it's like tapping a block. Okay, right? So tap /ɪ/
نتخيل أن لدينا صوت /ɪ/ وهو يشبه النقر على مكعب. حسناً، أليس كذلك؟ إذاً انقر /ɪ/
your block, say /ɪ/. Now we have the /iː/ sound which is longer. You can imagine that you have
على مكعبك، قل /ɪ/. الآن لدينا صوت /iː/ وهو أطول. يمكنك أن تتخيل أن لديك
your pencil and you're dragging it against something, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/. Good, /iː/. Alright, so
قلمك وأنت تسحبه على شيء ما، /iː/, /iː/, /iː/. جيد، /iː/. حسناً، إذاً
listen again, /ɪ/, /ɪ/ /iː/, /iː/. Notice that your jaw changes. So you have your tongue in a position
استمع مرة أخرى، /ɪ/, /ɪ/ /iː/, /iː/. لاحظ أن فكك يتغير. لسانك يكون في وضع
of your mouth higher for one than the other. It's all about the position of your tongue
أعلى في فمك لأحد الصوتين مقارنة بالآخر. الأمر كله يتعلق بوضع لسانك
in your mouth, /iː/ sound versus the /ɪ/, which is a little bit more relaxed. Okay. Do you hear
في فمك، صوت /iː/ مقابل صوت /ɪ/، الذي يكون أكثر استرخاءً قليلاً. حسناً. هل تسمع
the difference? Yes. Okay, excellent. So the short i, the /ɪ/ sound is a little bit
الفرق؟ نعم. حسناً، ممتاز. إذاً الـ i القصيرة، صوت /ɪ/، يختلف قليلاً
different than the /iː/ sound, the /iː/ is more, and it's /iː/ with the tongue higher up. We have
عن صوت /iː/، صوت /iː/ يكون أكثر...، وهو /iː/ مع اللسان مرفوعاً للأعلى. لدينا
the /ɪ/ sound with the jaw lower down, /iː/, you see my mouth, /iː/, alright? Okay, now you
صوت /ɪ/ مع الفك منخفضاً للأسفل، /iː/، أترى فمي، /iː/، حسناً؟ حسناً، الآن أنت
don't want to say /ɛ/, and this is, we have the /ɛ/ sounds like lead (metal), and we have the /ɪ/ sound
لا تريد أن تقول /ɛ/، وهذا هو، لدينا صوت /ɛ/ مثل في lead (معدن - maʿdin)، ولدينا صوت /ɪ/ مثل في lid،
like lid, and then we have the /iː/ sound like lead (to guide). And all of this depends on the position
ثم لدينا صوت /iː/ مثل في lead (يقود - yaqūd). وكل هذا يعتمد على وضع لسانك
of your tongue in your mouth. We have /ɛ/, /ɪ/, and /iː/. Repeat after me, /ɛ/, /ɪ/, /iː/   /ɛ/, /ɪ/, /iː/
في فمك. لدينا /ɛ/, /ɪ/, و /iː/. كرر بعدي، /ɛ/, /ɪ/, /iː/   /ɛ/, /ɪ/, /iː/
/iː/. Very good. Alright, so there are some differences in these sounds depending on the position
/iː/. جيد جداً. حسناً، إذاً هناك بعض الاختلافات في هذه الأصوات اعتماداً على وضع
of your tongue or jaw. So your mouth needs to be a little bit more open than with the
لسانك أو فكك. لذا يجب أن يكون فمك مفتوحاً أكثر قليلاً من عند نطق حرف
/i/ in Spanish. Your lips are relaxed, not smiling and not tight. So with the /ɪ/, it's like
الـ /i/ في الإسبانية. شفتاك مسترخيتان (mustarkhiyatān)، لا مبتسمتان ولا مشدودتان. لذا مع /ɪ/، الأمر أشبه
this little bit more and it is just /ɪ/, /ɪ/, right? Not /ɛ/. The tongue is a little high, a
بهذا قليلاً وهو فقط /ɪ/, /ɪ/, أليس كذلك؟ ليس /ɛ/. اللسان مرتفع قليلاً،
little to the front, and you'll need to relax your tongue a little. And it's a quick, a short
إلى الأمام قليلاً، وستحتاج إلى إرخاء لسانك قليلاً. وهو صوت سريع، قصير
quick sound like a little tap in the block sound, right? Okay. Feel it, relaxed. So try
سريع كأنه نقرة خفيفة على المكعب، أليس كذلك؟ حسناً. اشعر به، مسترخياً. إذاً حاول
making this sound yourself. You can mute it. Try making this sound yourself again. Let
إصدار هذا الصوت بنفسك. يمكنك كتم الصوت. حاول إصدار هذا الصوت بنفسك مرة أخرى. دعني
me hear you. Okay, /ɪ/, /iː/ And then /ɪ/, and /iː/, very good. Excellent. Okay. Alright.
أسمعك. حسناً، /ɪ/, /iː/ ثم /ɪ/, و /iː/, جيد جداً. ممتاز. حسناً. حسناً.
And just a little bit of this practice can make a big difference. So now I want you to
ومجرد القليل من هذا التدريب يمكن أن يحدث فرقاً كبيراً. إذاً الآن أريدك أن
show me... you can use a mirror or you can use the camera too. If you're too shy to use the
تريني... يمكنك استخدام مرآة أو يمكنك استخدام الكاميرا أيضاً. إذا كنت خجولاً جداً من استخدام
camera, that's okay if you want to use a mirror. So look at your mouth in the camera.
الكاميرا، لا بأس إذا أردت استخدام مرآة. إذاً انظر إلى فمك في الكاميرا.
Okay. Like this. You can see /ɪ/, /ɪ/, /ɪ/, /ɪ/, not /ɛ/, but /ɪ/... /ɪ/ , and /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, perfect.
حسناً. هكذا. يمكنك رؤية /ɪ/, /ɪ/, /ɪ/, /ɪ/, ليس /ɛ/, بل /ɪ/... /ɪ/ , و /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, /iː/, مثالي.
Alright, so you have the mouth, which has the lips spread wide, like a rubber band, for
حسناً، إذاً لديك الفم، حيث تكون الشفتان ممدودتين بشكل واسع، مثل شريط مطاطي، عند نطق
the /iː/ sounds, and it's high into the front, and you can feel a little bit of tension. So
أصوات /iː/، ويكون اللسان عالياً وفي المقدمة، ويمكنك الشعور ببعض التوتر. لذا
we have the, this one, which is the /iː/ sound, this is /ɪt/, and this one is /iːt/, right? Right.
لدينا، هذا، وهو صوت /iː/، هذا /ɪt/، وهذا /iːt/، أليس كذلك؟ صحيح.
It's a long, stretch sound, like pulling something. So you can imagine for the /iː/ sound
إنه صوت طويل وممتد، مثل سحب شيء ما. لذا يمكنك أن تتخيل عند نطق صوت /iː/
that you have, like rubber bands pulling in the corner of your mouth for this one.
أن لديك، مثل أشرطة مطاطية تسحب زاوية فمك لهذا الصوت.
So you can see this in the image here. You have the, /ɪ/ sounds here, which is the center
إذاً يمكنك رؤية هذا في الصورة هنا. لديك أصوات /ɪ/ هنا، وهي في المنتصف
in the front. The jaw is mid to close, and it's relaxed. And then the /iː/ sound is more spread
في الأمام. الفك متوسط إلى مغلق (al-fakku mutawassiṭ ilā mughlaq)، وهو مسترخٍ. ثم صوت /iː/ يكون أكثر انفراجاً (akthar infirājan).
apart. It's a little bit more closed, and the tongue is a little higher up. That's a
يكون مغلقاً أكثر قليلاً، واللسان أعلى قليلاً.
good job. Alright, so let's practice some of these. Here's an activity for us. You've got
عمل جيد. حسناً، إذاً لنتدرب على بعض هذه. إليكم نشاط لنا. لديك
your block and your pencil or pen, or whatever, or stick. Okay. So when you, when I say,
مكعبك وقلمك الرصاص أو الحبر، أو أي شيء، أو عصا. حسناً. إذاً عندما، عندما أقول،
or when, and when you say a word that has this short /ɪ/ sound, I want you to tap the block.
أو عندما، وعندما تقول كلمة تحتوي على صوت /ɪ/ القصير هذا، أريدك أن تنقر على المكعب.
Okay. And then when it has a long /iː/ sound, and then I want you to slide your stick. You ready?
حسناً. ثم عندما تحتوي على صوت /iː/ الطويل، أريدك أن تحرك عصاك. هل أنت مستعد؟
I'm ready. All right. So ship. Repeat, ship, ship.
أنا مستعد. حسناً. إذاً ship. كرر، ship, ship.
Uh-huh. Ship. Ship. Get. Bed. Bed. Beats. Beats. Ship. Ship. And ship.
أهأ. Ship. Ship. Get. Bed. Bed. Beats. Beats. Ship. Ship. و ship.
Sheep. Good. Sit. Good. Fill. Feel. Feel. Good. All right. We can practice a little bit more with this
Sheep. جيد. Sit. جيد. Fill. Feel. Feel. جيد. حسناً. يمكننا التدرب أكثر قليلاً على هذا الصوت /ɪ/.
/ɪ/ sound.
صوت /ɪ/.